Guide to the Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990 AIS.1977.33
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hymen Schlesinger Papers
1927-1990
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Schlesinger, Hymen
AIS.1977.33
13.6 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
Hymen Schlesinger was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1903 and began practicing law in 1927. His specialty was maritime law, but his political orientations led him to argue cases on behalf of labor unions, minorities, and accused Communists. The collection contains legal papers, correspondence, and news clippings particularly related to the above kinds of cases. Materials relating to the sedition trial of communist party district leader Steve Nelson are also present.
Biography
Hymen Schlesinger was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1903. He attended Princeton University and he attended Duquesne University's School of Law for one year, but earned his professional status as an attorney through an apprenticeship. (per information provided by his daughter) His specialty was maritime law, but his political orientations led him to argue cases on behalf of labor unions, minorities, and accused Communists. He was crucially involved in defending the foreign-born against deportation proceedings filed under the Walter-McCarran Act of 1952; and he successfully appealed disbarment proceedings that were brought against him by a local lawyers' committee accusing him of communist affiliation. Schlesinger passed away in Pittsburgh on February 5, 1976.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains legal papers, correspondence, and news clippings related to the career of Hymen Schlesinger. Cases involving deportation, denaturalization, civil rights of African Americans and alleged Communist party membership, as well as Schlesinger's own disbarment case and materials related to the trials of Communist district leader Steve Nelson, are particularly noteworthy. Also included are various publications pertaining to Communism and legal issues in Pennsylvania. In cases involving accused Communists, Schlesinger's main defense strategy was to attempt to discredit the testimony of government informers. Background files on informers, including Matthew Cvetic and Joseph Mazzei, are examples of this strategy. Another feature of the collection are related materials developed by University of Pittsburgh Labor Archivist David Rosenberg (retired). Overall, the Schlesinger Papers are one of the richest and most concentrated set of research materials available anywhere on the Red Scare in Pittsburgh.
Arrangement
Series I. Unions, 1944-1963
Series II. Background Material, 1946-1974
Series III. Disbarment and Reinstatement, 1943-1964
Series IV. Informers, 1950-1964
Series V. Individual Case Files, 1946-1975
Series VI. Cases by Category, 1947-1973
Series VII. Legal and Political Documents, 1942-1975
Series VIII. Personal Correspondence and Financial Papers, 1927-1975
Series IX. Organizations, 1946-1976
Series X. Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1961
Series XI. Card File Bibliography
Series XII. Publications, 1927-1976
Series XIII. Additional Cases
Access Restrictions
This collection contains materials protected by attorney-client privilege and, therefore, may be subject to review prior to researcher use. Access to privileged documents will be restricted in compliance with attorney-client confidentiality. This restriction in particular pertains to the two Barr-Walker cases, which have been moved to a box at the end of the collection. Please contact the Archives Service Center for more information.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Hymen Schlesinger in 1977.
Previous Citation
Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990, AIS.1977.33, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990, UELAB 77.33, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
M.Y. Steinberg Papers, AIS.1977.37, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Board of Education Records on Dorothy Albert, AIS.1992.09, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Steve Nelson Oral History Project Records, AIS.1978.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America Local 601 Records, UE 16-601, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Nelson, S., Barrett, J.R., Ruck, R. Steve Nelson, American Radical has been cataloged at the Archives Service Center and Hillman Library under the call number HX84 N44
Social action; Correspondence; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Jewish lawyers; United States -- Emigration and immigration -- Law and legislation; Law and socialism; Disbarment; Communism and Judaism; Civil rights and socialism; Lawyers; Communism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Personal papers; Seder, Morris; Serbian Progressive Club; Soldo, Charles; Stewart, Henry D., Jr.; Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born; Albert, Dorothy; Albert, Nathan; Pennsylvania. Court of Common Pleas (Allegheny County). Committee on Offences; American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born; Bennet, Henry; Civil Rights Congress (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Committee to Defend Jewish Culture (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Committee to Elect a Negro Congressman in 1956; Committee to End Sedition Laws; Communist Party of the United States of America (Western Pa.); Cvetic, Matthew; Nelson, Steve; Davis, Benjamin; Devunich, Steven; Hashmall, Frank; International Workers Order Cemetery (Wildwood, Pa.); Jewish Arts Committee (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Johnson, Arnold; Kemenovich, Steven; Mankin, Joseph; Mazzei, Joseph; McNeil, Allan Donald; Musmanno, Michael J.; Nuss, Antoinette; Pittsburgh Committee to Secure Justice for Morton Sobell; Santes, Gus; Schlesinger, Hymen; Schultz, Miriam
- Unions, 1944-1963; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains information regarding several of the labor unions that Schlesinger represented throughout his career. Present are legal papers, correspondence, and news clippings detailing several cases involving union locals, workers, and communism.
  - United Electrical Workers Local 610, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence and other documents concerning Schlesinger's representation of UE Local 610 before the War Labor Board about wage rate issues and also for some insurance matters. Legal papers on arbitration between General Electric and UE are also present.
  - United Electrical Workers Local 610 Current Matters, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence and memos from David Scribner of the UE Legal Department and materials regarding the Hartley Committee investigation of the UE in Evansville, Iowa, are present. There is also a letter from Thomas Quinn to Schlesinger which terminated the lawyer's professional relationship with the UE.
  - United Electrical Workers District 6 and Union Miscellany, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Included are correspondence, legal papers, constitutions, and by-laws relating to the UE v. Williamsport Battery Co. case. A handwritten letter by Schlesinger to AT&T on behalf of women telephone workers is also present.
  - IUMSWA Local 61, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    These files contain correspondence between this local of the Shipbuilders' Union and the Dravo Corporation, as well as legal briefs that were presented before the War Labor Board.
  - National Maritime Union, 1945-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    These files include correspondence regarding the discharge of two deckhands and copies of proposed legislation affecting maritime affairs.
  - United Office and Professional Workers of America Local 65, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Legal papers, correspondence, and clippings regarding insurance agents leaving their union due to accusations that the local was pursuing "Communist line policies" are present, as well as a report by Schlesinger compiled in an attempt to recover funds, property, and records.
  - Transport Workers Union, M.E. Weyant, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    Legal papers and correspondence concerning Schlesinger's work on behalf of union workers at the Pennsylvania Railroad works in Altoona who claimed illegal trusteeship was placed on their local and that they were denied their right to stand for election. Pamphlets from the Department of Labor explaining aspects of the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act are also present.
  - District 65 of the Distributive, Processing, and Office Workers Union of New York and New Jersey v. Kramer and McKague, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Correspondence regarding the use of union funds as bail money for members.
  - United Association of Journeymen Plumbers and Steamfitters, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    By-laws, minutes, and roll call of the union, as well as legal papers and correspondence concerning depositions in response to Local 449's lawsuit are present.
- Background Material, 1946-1974; II.
  This series contains information accumulated by Schlesinger that may have pertained to cases he was working on. Included are articles, booklets, manuals, and reports concerning pollution, communism, and civil rights. Some legal documents concerning civil rights and medical cases are also present.
  - Civil Rights, 1946-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Civil Rights Communications (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bail-Fund for the Civil Rights Congress of New York, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Communism in the United States, 1948-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Materials on Disarmament, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Material on Air Pollution in Allegheny County, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Medical Hearing Transcript (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gas Poisoning, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Regulations on Railings, Toe Boards, Open-Sided Floors, Platforms and Runways, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Occupational Safety and Health, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Regulations Handbook for Occupational Hazards, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Report of Proceedings of the 11th Constitutional Convention of the Transport Workers Union of American, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Accident/Injury/Damages, April-December 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Articles on Racism and Human Control (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Application Cards for a Book on Watergate (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - University of Akron Law Review, Spring 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Book Advertisements (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Defense Publications (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Leaflets (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Disbarment and Reinstatement, 1943-1964; III.
  In 1950, charges were filed claiming that Schlesinger was a member of the Communist party and calling for his disbarment. Hearings for the case began in 1954 and the struggle lasted for about ten years. This series consists of correspondence outlining Schlesinger's efforts to find representation, as well as of proceedings during the case. Legal papers filed by Schlesinger and the prosecution, the Committee on Offenses of the Courts of Common Pleas in Allegheny County, are also present.
  - Disbarment Correspondence, 1943, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Complaint Against Schlesinger, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Contempt of Court Citation, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings on Schlesinger, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Publications Possibly Used as Exhibits, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Depositions, Transcripts of Witnesses, Drafts for Respondent's Brief, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 32-37)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Offenses of the Allegheny County Court of Common Pleas Report and Respondent Briefs, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Legal Journal Digest of Disbarment Case, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Application for Supersedeas, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Drafts for Appeals Brief to Pennsylvania State Supreme Court, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Appeal Brief to the Pennsylvania Supreme Court, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7-16)
  - Brief of National Lawyers Guild in the Appeal of Schlesinger, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Comment on Recent Decisions of the U.S. Supreme Court in the Appeal of Schlesinger, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Brief in Behalf of the Committee on Offenses of the Courts of Common Pleas in the Appeal of Schlesinger, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Brief for Appellant in Appeal of Schlesinger, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, Appeal of Hymen Schlesinger Record, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 5-6)
  - Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, Appeal of Hymen Schlesinger Memorandum, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 7)
  - Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, Western District, Appeal of Hymen Schlesinger Reply Brief for Appellant, 1960 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Printing Bills, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 18-27)
  - Opinions of Justices, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Motion to Dismiss Complaint (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Brief for Respondent (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Citizens Committee to Protect the Right of Counsel (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Briefs of Related Cases (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Informers, 1950-1964; IV.
  This series contains newspaper clippings, leaflets, and legal papers documenting the contribution of undercover informers Joseph Mazzei and Matt Cvetic, who testified against hundreds of alleged communists at the House Un-American Activities Committee hearings during February and March of 1950. Phonodisc, reel to reel, and transcript copies of a speech by Cvetic at East Pittsburgh High School in March 19, 1950 are included. In the speech, Cvetic urged the Westinghouse union members to join the IUE instead of the UE which he denounced as a communist organization. Memos by Schlesinger regarding anti-Communist Judge Michael Musmanno are also present.
  - Joseph Mazzei, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Memos on Michael Musmanno, 1952-1964 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Matt Cvetic, 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 38-42)
  - Hearings Before the Committee on Un-American Activities, House of Representatives, Eighty-First Congress "Expose of the Communist Party of Western Pennsylvania Based Upon the Testimony of Matthew Cvetic", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Transcript of Cvetic Speech, March 19, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Phonodiscs of Cvetic Speech, March 19, 1950 (Box 4, Item 1-8)
  - Cvetic Speech, March 19, 1950 (Box 4, Reel 01-02)
- Individual Case Files, 1946-1975; V.
  The files in this series contain information related to individual cases and people Schlesinger represented. Many of the documents are legal papers from the trials, but correspondence and clippings are also present.
  - Political Cases, 1.
    This subseries contains files related to Schlesinger's politically charged cases. These particular cases dealt with alleged Communists and civil rights issues. Within the files are legal papers and correspondence.
    - Albert, Dorothy, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      This case involved a school teacher who was fired after Cvetic accused her of being a Communist. The file includes legal papers and minutes from the Board of Education discussing her case.
    - Albert, Nathan, 1948-1955 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
      Schlesinger defended Nathan Albert who was arrested under charges of attempting to incite a riot while trying to integrate Highland Park swimming pool in Pittsburgh. In a prior case, Albert appealed for compensation after he sued his employer, F.J. Kress Box Co., for wrongful dismissal. He was also alleged to be a member of the Communist party. Legal papers, correspondence, and clippings regarding the cases are present.
    - Bennett, Henry, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      This case was concerned with an African American defendant's issues regarding the setting of bail.
    - Davis, Benjamin, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      This case involves Benjamin Davis, an African American defendant who opposed various forms of segregation and racism within Allegheny County Jail. Davis served as a New York City councilman from 1943 to 1949 until he was convicted under the Smith Act for being a Communist. Legal papers, correspondence, and clippings regarding his case are present.
    - Devunich, Steven and Anna, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Schlesinger represented these alleged Communist party members who were to be denaturalized and deported under the Walter-McCarran Act. Included are legal papers and a leaflet from the Committee to Defend Anna and Steve Devunich.
    - Dudash, Mary, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      This file includes correspondence regarding Dudash's alleged Communist membership and the dismissal of her case.
    - Hashmall, Frank, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Hashmall was brought to court under the Smith Act, which made it illegal to advocate or teach others to advocate the overthrow of the United States government by force. This file contains legal papers and correspondence relating to Hashmall's case.
    - Kemenovich, Vincent and Katherine, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Schlesinger defended the Kemenovichs, alleged Communist party members, in this case in which the Croatian-born Kemenovichs were ordered to be deported under the Walter-McCarran Act. Included are legal papers and a leaflet from the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born.
    - McNeil, Allan Donald, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
      McNeil was a union organizer for the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America and a purported Communist party member. These files include legal papers and correspondence documenting his deportation case. There are also documents regarding the Committee to End Sedition Laws and regarding the House Un-American Activities Committee.
    - Mankin, Joseph, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      This file contains legal papers regarding Mankin's denaturalization and deportation case. He was a Lithuanian-born Jewish union organizer and alleged Communist who lived on the North Side of Pittsburgh.
    - Miller, Thomas, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 16-22)
      Schlesinger represented Miller, an alleged member of the Communist party, in this deportation case. Documents include legal papers relating to the case in which the Yugoslavian born Miller was accused of lying on his naturalization papers.
    - Moreland, James, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      This case involves an African American defendant who escaped from a Georgia prison camp. A judge in Pennsylvania refused to extradite Moreland to Georgia due to rumors of cruelty to African American prisoners. This file includes legal papers and clippings regarding this case.
    - Nuss, Antoinette, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 24-26)
      This file contains legal papers relating to Nuss' case in which she was removed from public assistance because she was an alleged member of the Communist party.
    - Patrick, Lonnie, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
      These files contain legal papers regarding Patrick being convicted of crimes. There are also documents relating to Patrick being beaten by guards while in prison and accusations of racism within the jail.
    - Pittsburgh Railways Company, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      These files include legal papers and news clippings regarding a public interest suit that attempted to block the increase of trolley rates. The papers mostly deal with the legality of the company raising fares without federal judge approval, but some clippings are concerned with the possible Communist party affiliation of some of those who took action against the company.
    - Polowishchak, Albert, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Schlesinger represented this United Mine Worker and alleged Communist party member in his deportation case under the Walter-McCarran Act. The file contains legal papers and correspondence regarding the case, as well as a Polish hearing transcript.
    - Salis, Bernard, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Salis was accused of being a member of the Communist party after being arrested for distributing flyers at the gates of the National Tube Works in McKeesport, Pa. Included in the file are legal papers and news clippings in which Schlesinger and Salis claim that his arrest was a violation of his First Amendment rights.
    - Santes, Gus, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
      This case includes legal papers, news clippings, and hearing transcripts relating to this deportation case in which Santes was accused of being a member of the Communist party. Also included is a leaflet from the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born regarding Santes' possible deportation under the Walter-McCarran Act.
    - Schultz, Miriam (Box 6, Folder 7)
      This file includes a transcript of Schultz's testimony before the House Un-American Activities Committee. She was the secretary of the Pittsburgh Civil Rights Congress and was accused of being a Communist.
    - Seder, Morris, 1953-1957 (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
      These files contain legal papers regarding Seder's deportation case in which he was accused of being a Communist. Legal papers regarding Seder's estate are also present.
    - Soldo, Charles, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 14-23)
      These files contain legal papers, transcripts, and clippings regarding this case in which Soldo, an accused Communist party member, was to be deported. In these files, Schlesinger attempts to discredit Matthew Cvetic, the informer who named Soldo as a Communist. Papers regarding Soldo's divorce proceedings are also present.
    - Spehar, Andrew, 1948-1956 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Spehar, a Yugoslavian non-citizen steel worker and coal miner living in West Virginia, was accused of being a Communist in this deportation case. Included are correspondence and legal papers relating to the case.
    - Spicer/John Welch Tunnell, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      This file includes a letter from Welch who was referred to Schlesinger by Spicer. In this correspondence he asks for representation in a case against the United States Marine Corp for improper dismissal when he threatened to publicize his report regarding helicopter malfunctions in Vietnam.
    - Stewart, Henry D., Junior, 1946-1950 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      This file includes legal papers regarding this case in which a father accused the War Department of racial discrimination during recruitment because his son was denied enlistment because he was an African American. Clippings in this file are concerned with a threat to stop all enlistment until the army desegregated and made recruitment standards equal for all men.
    - Students for a Democratic Society, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      Included in this file are legal papers and news clippings regarding an anti-war protest at South Hills High School started by female members of Students for a Democratic Society, of whom twenty six were arrested.
    - Terzich, Marko, 1953-1966 (Box 6, Folder 28-31)
      This file includes legal papers and correspondence regarding Terzich's deportation case in which he was accused of being a Communist party member by MattherCvetic and Mary Mazzei. Also present are his petition for naturalization after the deportation case ended and documents on his estate.
    - Tolsti, Joseph, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      This file contains legal papers from Tolsti's deportation case in which he was purported to have been a Communist. A transcript of the hearing is also present.
    - Young, Edward, 1962-1963; 2. (Box 6, Folder 33)
      This case involved an African American defendant who challenged issues regarding consecutive and concurrent sentences and asserted his right to a fair trial. This file contains legal papers and correspondence.
    - Steve Nelson, 1949-1959
      - United States v. Mesarosh, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)